<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>MattersEarthly - Research</title><link href="https://mattersearthly.co/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://mattersearthly.co/feeds/research.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://mattersearthly.co/</id><updated>2019-12-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><entry><title>UK Research Visit</title><link href="https://mattersearthly.co/posts/uk-research-visit.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2019-12-19T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2019-12-19T00:00:00+02:00</updated><author><name>Michael 0</name></author><id>tag:mattersearthly.co,2019-12-19:/posts/uk-research-visit.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A summary of my research visit to Bath, England&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;From mid-October to mid-November 2019, I was in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; for a research visit. The opportunity to collaborate closely, exchange ideas, learn from another perspective while in a different work environment is always welcome. &lt;a href= "https://kaute.fi/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;KAUTE&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, The Finnish Science Foundation for Technology and Economics, funded the research visit. While in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt;, I worked with  &lt;a href= "https://www.rachelburrows.net" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Dr Rachel Burrows&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Digital Interventions for the Marginalised in Society&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The aim of the visit was to investigate the use of digital interventions to address the needs of the marginalised in society, to understand the challenges in designing these interventions and the opportunities they avail.  The marginalised could include asylum seekers, low-income communities, those without access to financial services, those living in rural areas and so on. In the initial plan, we were to focus on homelessness but decided to first review contemporary research on marginalisation before investigating digital interventions for the homeless. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Marginalised communities face significant barriers and inequities in entitlement and access to even basic needs. These include limited access to digital content and/or know-how, communication difficulties, lack of social support and other socioeconomic challenges leading to their stigmatisation. This prevents the marginalised from taking part in societal interactions and navigating the complex and ever-changing social system. For these reasons, the marginalised communities represent unique, urgent and poorly understood challenges with the potential for many technological solutions. There needs to be an in-depth understanding of these unique design challenges posed before implementing any digital intervention.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the visit, we analysed literature on different marginalised communities to find the common themes from research. Among the key findings from our initial research was the important role of social support. Social support from peers who help to relay important information to those without digital means and from social workers. Social workers who act as mediators and help marginalised communities to find relevant information. Another important finding was the role of policies in amplifying or mitigating the delivery of services. Policymakers should understand the unique challenges of marginalised communities in order not to enact policies detrimental to their wellbeing. Welfare policies and systems can influence the delivery of services; and the individual capacity of a homeless person, for example, could impact their willingness to, and the way they interact with the service systems. This is because the way systems are configured affects the delivery of services and the quality of the service provided.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Th next steps after the visit are to submit for publication the results of our review and to integrate the findings from the review into at least one other study. The review focuses on investigating existing digital approaches to addressing the needs of the homeless and the outcomes of these. The following study will focus on understanding inclusion and user values from systems thinking perspective.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Research"/><category term="research"/><category term="technology"/><category term="marginalisation"/></entry><entry><title>Doctoral Defence</title><link href="https://mattersearthly.co/posts/doctoral-defence.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2018-05-15T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2018-05-15T00:00:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Michael 0</name></author><id>tag:mattersearthly.co,2018-05-15:/posts/doctoral-defence.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;PhD defences vary widely in style and focus, often probing methodology, terminology, and practical relevance. Key questions test understanding, research implications, and generalisability. Personal experience highlights the importance of preparation, adaptability, and clear communication.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;During my doctoral studies, I attended a few PhD defences. Sometimes I made notes of the important points and questions raised whenever I attended any defence. Some opponents concentrate on the methodological approach and the rationale for the overall study, whereas others focus on the definition of terms and the practical implications of the research — or a bit of both.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As our group’s research focuses on persuasive systems design and behaviour change, the opponent during one of my colleague’s defences asked for an actual situation where an application could change behaviour. This was not about one particular system, rather a broader view of the effectiveness of persuasive or behaviour change support systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Defences also differ in their format depending on the opponent. Some are like a debate, whereas others are more of a conversation. In the former, the opponent tests the pressure points of the candidate and tries to gauge their responses to tough questions. The latter is a more relaxed setting where the opponent engages in a conversation with the candidate to understand their thought process during the doctoral studies and how the thesis process developed. There are also opponents who preview the planned questions and their level of difficulty.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some questions or issues that often come up during PhD defences include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why did you engage in this area of research?  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What did you hope to achieve from the research?  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;On what grounds did you decide whether some works apply to your work?  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The overall plan — whether you met initial goals, and the reasoning behind the order of articles (for article-based theses).  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What was the toughest part of your work?  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Comments about the inconsistent definition of terms.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why the focus on a particular topic and/or context?  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Considering whether awareness of the research methodology is part of a researcher’s obligation.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Highlighting the gaps in the literature that the research questions address.  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Research perspective:&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;When thinking about the results, does culture play a role (depending on the type of research and the target population)? Consider the context of the research and how it might apply to different ethnic backgrounds. Address the applicability of the research and to which audiences it applies — the key knowledge gap.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Summary of the studies:&lt;/strong&gt;  &lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would have happened if the studies were in reverse order?  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What would it have done to the significance of the results and contributions of the work?  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;What are the most surprising findings from the studies done on the research topic?  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;How do the overall findings relate to the published work and what are their implications?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Subjective Reflection of My Defence&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My doctoral defence was not the greatest of presentations, but I addressed my opponent’s questions well and we had a pleasant discussion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Considering how the morning of the defence went, it was a relief to get through the presentation without major issues. I tried to rehearse, but I could barely string together two clear sentences — even while presenting to my partner and brother-in-law! That raised the nervousness scale to a level I did not want a few hours before the main event. Luckily, I got over it quickly and was relaxed by the time of the defence.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The beginning of the presentation was tense, but as with many of my presentations, it got better as it progressed. If only I could present as freely as I write — often when presenting I struggle to find the right words and end up repeating the same basic terms. Despite these minor issues, the presentation went well and from the audience’s point of view, there weren’t any confusing issues. At least one of my friends, who was not familiar with the topic, said they understood the presentation and could follow the exchange with my opponent, which was a good sign.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond the specifics of particular studies, my opponent also tried to gauge my understanding of the implications — not only of my research but of the field of persuasive systems research in general. There were a few speculative questions in which I had to think about the broader implications of my research and how to adapt the findings to different problem situations. This was important, as my dissertation did not concentrate on a particular problem domain but focused on improving the design and development of persuasive systems by adapting concepts from other scientific fields (e.g., psychology and software engineering) and investigating how persuasive features are implemented in existing systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I did not have a proper response to some questions, as expected, but this was not the main aim. Rather, the goal was to test my understanding of the implications of the research for practice, and the generalisability of my findings. How could the practices, design principles, and frameworks outlined in my research apply in different problem domains? Which are the best strategies to choose in these contexts?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The debate helped break down persuasive systems (design) research into digestible steps that anyone could understand (I think). We did not need to explain any ambiguous terms, and I especially liked that the opponent did not dwell too much on research methods. Unlike some defences, we spent little time on “why this method over that” type of questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now comes the tough part — how to move beyond or extend the studies and develop new research directions. 🙂&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Research"/><category term="PhD"/><category term="research"/><category term="doctoral defence"/></entry></feed>