<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>MattersEarthly - Writing</title><link href="https://earthlymatters.co/" rel="alternate"/><link href="https://earthlymatters.co/feeds/writing.atom.xml" rel="self"/><id>https://earthlymatters.co/</id><updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+03:00</updated><entry><title>The Challenges of Academic Writing</title><link href="https://earthlymatters.co/blog/academic-writing.html" rel="alternate"/><published>2020-08-26T00:00:00+03:00</published><updated>2020-08-26T00:00:00+03:00</updated><author><name>Michael 0</name></author><id>tag:earthlymatters.co,2020-08-26:/blog/academic-writing.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Academic writing often suffers from poor time allocation, disorganized structure, and the tendency to edit while writing. Prioritizing research, separating writing from editing, and focusing on completion over perfection can significantly improve productivity and outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="bigger"&gt; Spend 40% of the time researching, 20% actually writing and 40% editing and rewriting. &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sometime back, I took part in a webinar about academic writing and the issues that lead to challenges when reporting or documenting research. The webinar was hosted by &lt;a href= "https://www.publicationcoach.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener"&gt;Daphney Grant&lt;/a&gt;. The points raised in the webinar are those I have often struggled with in my research and in projects, especially in the initial stages when there is a lack of clarity. A summary of the issues discussed in the&amp;nbsp;webinar. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure to budget time effectively. Tell me about&amp;nbsp;it!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Editing while writing, which is destructive&amp;nbsp;because:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it is like multitasking (an illusion of&amp;nbsp;work)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it makes writing more uncomfortable (and more&amp;nbsp;difficult)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;it makes you a bad editor because you don&amp;#8217;t have enough distance and perspective on your&amp;nbsp;work. &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A suggested trick is to write in 3-point type, which is too small to read. If you can&amp;#8217;t read it, you can&amp;#8217;t edit! Also, developing the habit of promissory notes&amp;#8230; writing a note in the document to remind yourself to check a fact later and don&amp;#8217;t stop&amp;nbsp;writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lack of good systems for storing documents… besides using reference managers, saving documents with multiple tags gives you different ways to find articles later and ideas about&amp;nbsp;writing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Failure to keep a research diary detailing the history of the research as it unfolds. The diary should not contain any research itself, but records opinions about the research. Keeping a research diary also allows you to maintain a writing habit, a low-risk place to write while doing&amp;nbsp;research.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poor editing skills. Editing should be more specific than just reading the same text repeatedly and trying to make it better. As researchers, we should break the habit of editing while writing and re-reading what we have written right after writing.  &lt;br&gt;
There are two types of editing: &lt;strong&gt;Substantive (developmental) and copyediting (line)&lt;/strong&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Substantive editing relates entirely to the &lt;strong&gt;content&lt;/strong&gt;. Does the material make sense, is it logical, is it persuasive, is everything in the right order, missing information,&amp;nbsp;etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Copyediting relates to &lt;strong&gt;rules&lt;/strong&gt;. Checking the spelling, average sentence length, antecedents, grammar,&amp;nbsp;etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The two types of editing require different approaches. The best way to do substantive editing is to take a break first (incubating). It is important to address your work with fresh eyes, and your eyes will not be fresh if you have recently read your document many times. Ideally, you should have forgotten about what you wrote, and then you will approach the work in a similar mindset to the&amp;nbsp;readers. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you’ve had the break, review the work while reading it aloud and ask yourself whether it will make sense to the uninitiated reader.
Later, when copyediting use software or a copyeditor to help check for any&amp;nbsp;errors.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aspiring to spend way too much time working and end up wasting much of that time. Set small reasonable goals, e.g. writing 200 words a day or for 15 minutes every day.  &lt;br&gt;
Book recommendation: &lt;strong&gt;The Now Habit by Neal Fiore&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An accountability system that is too weak. For want of a nail&amp;#8230; The small daily goals you cannot achieve because of a lack of&amp;nbsp;accountability. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perfectionists tend to procrastinate. Procrastination is about poor impulse control. Perfectionism can be a problem, and we should start forcing ourselves to be less than perfect — for example, by handing in assignments before they feel perfect, or sharing “crappy” drafts often.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is more important to get the work done and on time than to do it perfectly. Perfectionism can hold your work back.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Book recommendation:&lt;/strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;The Checklist Manifesto: If you can talk, you can write.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Rewriting should take time.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
If you spend 20% of the time writing, then you should have plenty of time for rewriting.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We should aspire to write &lt;em&gt;crappy first drafts&lt;/em&gt;. That should be the goal — if your first draft looks excellent, it probably means you’re spending too much time editing while writing and not enough time editing afterward, once you’ve had some distance.&lt;/p&gt;</content><category term="Writing"/><category term="writing"/><category term="academia"/></entry></feed>